

INFORMATICS AND COMPUTING ENGINEER

Gondomar, Porto

🛮 (+351) 933 235 253 | 🗷 goncalojmarantes@gmail.com | 🌴 goncalomarantes.com | 🖸 marantesss | 🖫 goncalomarantes | 💆 @marantesss

Summary.

Software Engineer with 2 years experience in web development working at small and medium-sized enterprises. a Master's degree in Informatics and Computing Engineering from the Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto. Working mostly with web technologies. Advocate of functional programming. Passionate about open-source, software architecture, containerization, CI/CD, software development methodologies, project management, database technologies and web development.

Education

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto

R. Dr. Roberto Frias, 4200-465 Porto

BACHELOR'S & MASTER'S DEGREE IN INFORMATICS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2022

- Dissertation: A framework to support the deployment of circular economy ecosystems
- Software Engineering
- · Requirements Engineering
- Database Technologies
- Project Management
- · Software Testing

Experience

Intuitivo Porto

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Aug. 2023 - Present

- Using React and JSS to develop to the Intuitivo web platform, and ExpressJS with PostgreSQL for API development
- Developed a native desktop version of the App with anti-cheat features using ElectronJS
- Designed and implemented a performance test suite using Locust to stress test the platform for Portugal's national exams with around 200k concurrent users
- Implemented an in-memory database solution for fast data access using Redis
- · Designed, developed, tested and implemented Intuitivo's UI component library

Infraspeak Porto

FRONTEND DEVELOPER Sep. 2022 - Aug. 2023

- Used VueJS with Typescript and SCSS to contribute to Infraspeak's web client
- Tinkered with PHP, Laravel and PHPUnit to contribute to Infraspeak's web API
- Used Git and Gitlab as version control systems and Jira as issue tracker and planner applications
- Designed, developed, tested and open-sourced a tool to batch migrate the Infraspeak client codebase from the deprecated Vue Class-based syntax to the Options API Syntax to aid in Vue 3 migration
- Invited speaker at Portugal.vue

INESC TECPorto

RESEARCH ASSITANT Nov. 2021 - Aug. 2022

- Developed my master's dissertation which includes a requirements engineering and design framework for circular economy ecosystems
- Took part in the H2020 European innovation project CircThread
- Studies the literature on Industrial Digital Platforms and Ecosystems, Circular Economy and Innovation Ecosystems
- Interviewed European industrial organizations related with home appliances and energy systems life cycle to elicit organizational and technological requirements
- Wrote industrial scenarios for stakeholder discussion, validation and vision alignment
- · Created a tool to test ecosystem dynamics and informational dependencies between multiple actors of the product life cycle
- · Built businesses process with BPMN to formalize platform experience integration with current industrial processes and work systems

ZeroZero Vila Nova de Gaia

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Jun. 2021 - Sep. 2021

- Developed "Project: Orwell", a web service to aid in the identification and categorization of website visitors. Extracts information from web requests, such as IP address, location, page visits, etc.
- Designed the web application interface with the help of Figma and Affinity Design. Built the entire page layout, components and interactions
- Developed the web interface using React, Bulma and SCSS; external and internal APIs with NodeJS, ExpressJS and KnexJS; database using PostgreSQL and PL/pgSQL; cache using Redis and server configuration with Traefik
- Developed server unit tests with Jest and Supertest
- Containerized the whole service with Docker and Docker Compose, compatible with different environments
- · Configured ZeroZero's internal GitLab instance with GitLab runners and CI/CD configuration
- · Configured automatic project deployment to virtual private server

Projects

Vue Class Decorators to Options API Transpiler

(https://github.com/Marantesss/decorators-to-object-api-transpiler)

Personal 202

Developed a program to batch migrate Vue Single File Components using a class-based syntax with vue-property-decorators package, to Options
API syntax

• Wrote a blog post about the technical implementation and architectural decisions behind this tool

Glass Base (https://github.com/Marantesss/glass-base)

Personal

- Developed a web dashboard and REST API to visualize data from the Portuguese government public contract platform. This application stores, serves and presents data in a more user friendly way, with metrics, charts and table
- Designed the dashboard with Figma. Developed the dashboard with NuxtJS and TailwindCSS, server development was done in NodeJS, ExpressJS and KnexJS, relational database was developed in PostgreSQL

Extracurricular Activity

IEEE University of Porto Student Branch

Porto, Portugal

CORE MEMBER & VICE-CHAIRMAN ON 2019

Nov. 2017 - Dec.2022

- Helped organize events (RetroJam 2019, REC 2020) and workshops (C++, Git)
- Contributed to the development of the student branch's website
- · Designed multiple branding materials

Licenses & Certifications

17 **Certificate of Proficiency in English**, University of Cambridge

Porto, Portugal

2017 **B Driver's License**, IMT

Porto, Portugal